Guide to the W. Stebbins Smith Papers 1799, 1840s-1935 MS 575
New-York Historical Society
W. Stebbins Smith papers
1799, 1840s-1935
New-York Historical Society
Smith, W. Stebbins (William Stebbins), approximately 1846-1937
Smith, Chauncey, 1810-1883
MS 575
50 Linear feet in 49 record cartons and 1 flat box.
The collection includes the papers of Bronx, New York-based lawyer, W. Stebbins Smith, who practiced from the 1870s to the early 1930s. To a much lesser extent, the collection also includes the papers of Smith's father, Chauncey Smith, who was also a lawyer practicing from perhaps the 1840s to the 1880s. Smith's practice primarily encompassed real estate and general estate matters in the Bronx and Westchester County, and the collection reflects that. In addition to the many individuals represented by Smith, the collection includes records related to the real estate transactions of various Methodist Episcopal churches which engaged Smith. As a member of the Bronx community himself, Smith's papers also include a sizable amount of correspondence and other documents related to local politics, trade, transit, and charitable causes. The legal papers have not been processed and access restrictions apply to them.
Arrangement
The collection is preliminarily organized in three series:
Series I. Correspondence/Contents of Letter Boxes
Series II. Bound Volumes
Series III. Legal Matters
Biographical / Historical
W. (William) Stebbins Smith was born about 1846. He attended Columbia Law School, graduating in the 1870s. By 1881, he had joined his father, Chauncey Smith, who was also a lawyer, in practice in the Bronx, New York. Smith's practice seems to have centered principally on real estate property transactions and general estate administration. He lived in the Bronx and practiced law there for about 65 years, retiring in the mid-1930s. He seems to have worked out of the same office at 462 East 167th Street for most, and perhaps all, of his career (though the city changed the building number at least once during his ownership). Smith was active in various civic, professional, and religious organizations. As one example, he served a two-year term in 1903-04 as the first president of the Bronx County Bar Association. Smith died in Kingston, NY, in 1937 at age 91.
(The above note was based on Smith's obituary in the New York Times, other on-line references, and documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Some access restrictions apply to the documents in Series III; see the notes at that series for details.
Most of the materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase, February 15, 1938, from George W. Waterman (likely Smith's son-in-law), through Edmund B. Child.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes the papers of Bronx, New York-based lawyer, W. Stebbins Smith, who practiced from the 1870s to the early 1930s. To a much lesser extent, the collection also includes the papers of Smith's father, Chauncey Smith, who was also a lawyer practicing from perhaps the 1840s to the 1880s.
Smith's practice primarily encompassed real estate and general estate matters, and the collection reflects that. Centered principally on the Bronx real estate market, the collection includes title abstracts, maps, deeds, mortgages, lease and other agreements, tax and other assessments, damage claims, client-related correspondence, etc. There is print matter related to auctions, tax liens, foreclosure sales, and the like. In addition to the many individuals represented by Smith, the collection includes records related to the real estate transactions of various Methodist Episcopal churches that engaged Smith.
As a member of the Bronx community himself, Smith's papers also include a sizable amount of correspondence and other documents related to local politics, trade, transit, and charitable causes.
Related Materials
It appears that when the W. Stebbins Smith collection was first acquired by N-YHS in 1938, it included much more material related to Smith's father, Chauncey Smith, than is currently in the collection. That material was separated into a different collection, the Chauncey Smith papers. There is no finding aid currently for those papers, but they are cataloged in Bobcat; follow this link. Some W. Stebbins Smith-related documents can also be found in those Chauncey Smith papers.
A single W. Stebbins Smith document was cataloged in the AHMC collection: W. Stebbins Smith title fee payment, 1907 May 7 (AHMC - Smith, W. Stebbins).
N-YHS also holds the Mysterious Star Club Minutes, 1864 Sept. 12-1865 Aug. 2 (BV Mysterious Star Club). W. Stebbins Smith was an officer of that club.
The New-York Historical Society's museum holds W. Stebbins Smith's notary public seal press: https://blog.nyhsdev2.org/exhibit/seal-embosser
Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Land titles -- Registration and transfer -- Cases.; Probate law and practice -- New York (State); Real estate lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Real property -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Westchester County (N.Y.); Cadastral maps.; Insurance policies.; Lecture notes.; Legal files.; Letters (correspondence); Property records.; Methodist Episcopal Church
- Series I. Correspondence/Contents of Letter Boxes, 1899-1935; 11 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series holds the content of about 52 letterboxes in the collection, dating from about 1899 to about 1935. The boxes had deteriorated so the contents were removed into archival folders and rehoused in October 2021, but the arrangement of the folders retained that of the letterboxes.
  The series primarily includes incoming letters, and also holds drafts or copies of outgoing letters and various forms of print matter and ephemera (e.g., newspaper clippings, advertisements, pamphlets, political handbills, programs, business cards, solicitations for donations, etc.).
  The correspondence was only skimmed for subject matter content by the archivist. It appears that there is some correspondence here related to Smith's clients/legal matters, but these seem to be mostly of a transactional nature (e.g., arrangements for title searches, inquiries about potential matters, etc.); more client-related correspondence is likely found with the legal files in Series III.
  More extensive here is Smith's correspondence on personal affairs and on matters that lie on the blurry boundary between personal and professional interests. These include documents related to elections and politics (filed under "P") and to Smith's apparent support for the Republican Club of the City of New York (under "R"). A consistently sizable amount of material over the years is found filed under "C" for various churches, most especially those of the Methodist Episcopal denomination in the Bronx and New York City generally, and for various Christian charitable causes, such as the YMCA. Under "T" can be found extensive material from the North Side Board of Trade in the City of New York (renamed in 1914 as the Bronx Board of Trade in the City of New York). While some of this material is of a general solicitation nature, some is specific to Smith and reflects his deeper support of some of these institutions and activities.
  Arrangement
  The series retains the order of the original letterboxes from which the contents were removed. Based on the original label on the spine of the boxes, most of the letterboxes held documents from one of two 6-month periods for each year (January 1-July 1 and July 1-January 1). It seems likely, though, that some of the boxes held documents from somewhat outside their stated date range. A few letterboxes explicitly held documents from longer periods, that is, one or more years.
  Within each box, documents were further arranged alphabetically by Smith, but how that was applied by him was idiosyncratic and somewhat inconsistent over time. No rearrangement was done when the archivist rehoused the documents. Although many documents were filed by correspondent surname, much more was filed by a keyword or general subject regardless of the name. As examples: Banks tend to be under B; miscellaneous Bronx-oriented organizations are also under B; churches and Christian associations tend to be under C; lawyer or legal associations under L; candidates for public office and election matters under P for politics, except those specific to the Republican Party, which is under R; trade or transit organizations tend to be under T. Nonetheless, despite these filing trends, there are some inconsistencies in how names were filed over time.
  - Correspondence (17 folders), circa 1899-1903 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-17)
    Some 1901 letterbox content may have been removed and may be that found in box 17 (see Series III).
  - Correspondence (16 folders), 1903 July-1906 January (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-16)
    The letter box for January-July 1904 was missing when the documents were rehoused to archival folders in October 2021; these are likely found mixed with the legal papers in box 17 and possibly 37 (see Series III). For letterbox July 1905-January 1906, this box holds correspondents A-S; T-Z is in the next box.
  - Correspondence (14 folders), 1905 July-1908 January (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-14)
    For letterbox July 1905-January 1906, this box holds correspondents T-Z; A-S is in the prior box.
  - Correspondence (14 folders), 1908-1910 January (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-14)
  - Correspondence (14 folders), 1910-1912 January (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-14)
  - Correspondence (21 folders), 1912-1914 July (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-21)
  - Correspondence (19 folders), 1914 July-1917 January (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-19)
  - Correspondence (20 folders), 1917-1920 July (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-20)
  - Correspondence (20 folders), 1920 July-1924 January (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-20)
    The letterbox for the period July 1921-January 1922 was not found in the collection in October 2021; the related documents are possibly in box 37 (see Series III).
  - Correspondence (23 folders), 1924-1928 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-23)
  - Correspondence (20 folders), 1929-circa 1935 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-20)
- Series II. Bound Volumes, 1853-1932; 4 Linear feet
  The series includes the various bound volumes in the collection. These include 14 volumes of copies of Smith's outgoing, typed letters from 1904-1925. (Series I includes handwritten drafts of at least some of Smith's outgoing letters.) One volume includes summaries of events/actions related to Smith's legal matters for years 1913-1924, which can serve as something of a guide for some of the documents found in Series III. Five volumes relate to his work on damage claims and assessments in connection with street openings. 15 volumes include Smith's notes he took as a student at Columbia Law School and two volumes include his later reference notes on various case law. Other volumes, many of them pocket size and sometimes obscure in purpose, are account books (including one of 1883 for the People's Ice Company), daily calendars, receipt and check stubs, and a few other small items.
  Arranged by subject matter/content.
  - Letterpress copybooks (outgoing correspondence) (8 volumes), 1904 May-August 1914 (Offsite-box 12, Volume 1-8)
  - Letterpress copybooks (outgoing correspondence) (6 volumes), 1914 September-1925 July (Offsite-box 13, Volume 1-6)
  - Notes on Smith's cases, 1913-1924 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 1)
    Volume includes a record of Smith's cases with daily entries of events related to each case.
  - Chauncey Smith notebook, 1866-1874 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 2)
    A small notebook dated 1874, with no entries, but with a small number of letters and other documents to Chauncey Smith.
  - Index, circa 1868-1900? (Offsite-box 14, Volume 3`)
    Volume holds various lists of records: list of maps on hand, map abstracts, catalogue of books, etc. Appears to have been started in the 1880s, with record of earlier dated items, and extending to perhaps 1900.
  - Notes on street openings, 1890s (Offsite-box 14, Volume 4)
  - "Bender's Lawyer's Diary and Directory", 1914-1915 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 5)
    Published book with various references for lawyers, with daily calendars that include some entries by Smith.
  - "Diary", 1926 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 6)
    Appears to be a courtesy daily calendar printed for publicity purposes by the National Title Guaranty Company. Smith made no entries in the book.
  - Pocket calendar diary, 1932 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 7)
    Has some entries by Smith.
  - Assessments and Awards (3 volumes), undated (Offsite-box 14, Volume 8-10)
    Assessments for 138th Street, Morris Ave., Willis Ave., 149th Steeet, Westchester Ave., Cliff Street, Tinton Ave., 156th Street, and 161st Street. Awards for damages on the same, and Prospect Ave.
  - Account book for Webster Avenue damages, undated (Offsite-box 14, Volume 11)
  - Account book of People's Ice Company, 1883 (Offsite-box 14, Volume 12)
  - Notes on case law (2 volumes), 1880s?-1920s? (Offsite-box 15, Volume 1-2)
    These do not appear to be Smith's cases, but rather notes in alphabetical order by topic concerning cases on various matters for legal reference.
  - Notebooks from Columbia College Law School (15 volumes), 1869-1870 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 3-17)
  - Account books (10 volumes), 1870-1900, undated (Offsite-box 15, Volume 18-27)
    Small account books, most undated, and most unclear as to purpose. Some related to groceries. One holds a schedule (1893) of presumably local baseball teams, with some scores.
  - Bank deposit books (2 volumes), 1853, 1917 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 28-29)
    Account of John Golder (1853) and Patrick Kerley (1917).
  - Receipt stubs (9 volumes), 1901-1919 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 30-38)
    Appears to be primarily rent payment receipts.
  - Check stubs, 1869-1870 (Offsite-box 15, Volume 39)
    Chauncey Smith checkbook (only stubs with notations in book). Other checkbooks and stubs of Chauncey Smith are found in various boxes in Series III.
  - Billfold (empty), undated (Offsite-box 15)
- Series III. Legal Papers (Access Restrictions Apply), 1799, 1840s-1935; 35 Linear feet
  The series primarily includes records concerning the various legal matters handled by W. Stebbins Smith. The series has not been processed and so this description is based on a quick survey of the content of each box. Perhaps half of the series remains in its original condition of tri-folded documents tied together in bundles, often several inches in depth. The rest of the documents are loose and so their relationship, if any, to surrounding documents is unclear.
  Overall, the legal matters appear to center, perhaps exclusively so, on real estate property transactions and general estate matters (i.e., administration of wills). These appear to principally concern Bronx communities such as Morrisania, Melrose, Olinville, Highbridgeville, West Farms, and Wakefield, and others not noted. Property in areas outside the Bronx, such as White Plains, are also represented in the series. Transactions include purchases, sales, and leases of property, as well as claims related to property ownership, such as tax liens, assessments for improvements, damage claims against or on behalf of owners, and the like.
  Generally, it appears that Smith represented individuals, not corporate/institutional interests. One major exception to this is that he seems to have often represented local Methodist Episcopal churches, including the Centreville African Methodist Episcopal Church, in their real estate matters, as reflected in the series.
  Documents in the series include title abstracts, deeds, insurance policies, contracts/agreements, wills, mortgages, assessments, damage claims, property maps, tax bills, and other real estate transaction-related documents. Print matter is found throughout, such as newspaper clippings of real estate auctions and other related matters, auction broadsides, tax lien and other property-related lists, etc. There is extensive, though scattered, correspondence. Much of this relates to legal matters, but much also relates to other matters as reflected in the correspondence of Series I. Some of this appears to have formerly been in letterboxes such as those represented in Series I, while other letters are loose.
  The majority of the documents, dating from the 1880s-1930s, relate to the activities of W. Stebbins Smith. The series also includes many documents from the 1840s-1870s that relate to Smith's father, Chauncey Smith, who was also a lawyer. There is some overlap in the 1870s and perhaps in the early 1880s as the father and son partnered for a brief time. Some documents relate to Smith's handling of Chauncey's estate. It is also likely that some of the early documents do not relate to Chauncey's activities, but were compiled by W. Stebbins Smith as part of his file on matters of a later date.
  In the container list, the phrase "Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters" is used to indicate that the above-described broad mix of documents is present in the box. In some instances, particular document types or legal matters could be readily discerned on a quick survey and those were also noted in the container list, but should not be taken as encompassing a box's entire content. None of the tri-folded bundles were unbound during the survey so the survey could only perceive the content based on the description from the outermost document (which was often the title abstract with the name of the matter). Date ranges are rough and based on the (relatively few) viewed documents.
  The series has not been processed and generally there is no organization to the documents. Overall, each box in the series holds documents from a wide date range and on various matters. Documents on what appears to be the same or related matters are found in more than one box (e.g., the names John B. Suffern, George Stolz, Jennie Irving, and John Devoe are among the many that appear on documents throughout the boxes in the series). However, much of the material is tri-folded and tied together in thick bundles, with presumably some relationship that can possibly be determined from the labeling on the outermost document.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Because of the condition of the documents in the series, access requires mediation by N-YHS staff. Patrons are permitted to review the contents of the boxes in the series, but will need to consult with the manuscripts curator or processing archivist before accessing each box. Further, patrons wishing to have particular bundles of documents opened will need to have that done by N-YHS processing staff. Accordingly, patrons should be aware that special arrangements and likely multiple visits will be needed for use of the documents in this series.
  - Unprocessed files, 1853-1920s (Offsite-box 16)
    About 1/2 box of loose documents, including, among others: check stubs, 1853-64; newspaper clippings, 1860s; manuscript map of land in West Farms owned by Rebecca Marcher, 1880; draft of bill of legal expenses (rolled), 1902; certificate to Smith for his contribution to the Henry Hudson monument at Spuyten Duyvil Hill; correspondence re: Smith vs. Cosmopolitan, circa 1919; and miscellaneous tax bills, loan applications, requests for mortgage placements; etc.
  - Unprocessed files, 1860s-1910s (Offsite-box 17)
    Includes, among other documents: check stubs, 1860s; partial(?) contents of one or more letterboxes, 1901, 1904; and loose pile of letters, clippings, etc., 1870s-1910s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1900s (Offsite-box 18)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Bulk is dated 1890s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1920s (Offsite-box 19)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Bulk 1880s-circa 1901, with some documents ranging to the 1920s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1931 (Offsite-box 20)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Bundles of bills, 1880s, 1920s, 1931.
  - Unprocessed files, 1870s-1926 (Offsite-box 21)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters.
  - Unprocessed files, 1799, 1854-1900s (Offsite-box 22)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. There is a 1799 indenture.
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1935 (Offsite-box 23)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Appears to have a relatively large amount of general correspondence from 1893, including some concerning the estate of Chauncey Smith. 1932 bills. Some 1935 correspondence from the city re: tax lien information.
  - Unprocessed files, 1860s-1933 (Offsite-box 24)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Checks, 1860s. Bundles of bills, 1870s, 1881, 1928, 1929, 1933. Correspondence, 1898-1899. Pile of insurance policies, 1890s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1852-1925 (Offsite-box 25)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Tax sale notices 1910s-1925.
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1920 (Offsite-box 26)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. There are a few documents concerning the Centreville African Methodist Episcopal Church, which was represented by Smith, and its title and sale of property in Westchester, circa 1890s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1930s (Offsite-box 27)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Bundle of bills, 1920. Tax sale notices, 1920s-30s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1924 (Offsite-box 28)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Many more documents here concerning the Centreville African Methodist Episcopal Church; appears to relate to the sale of their property and graveyard, with plans to re-inter the remains at Woodlawn (apparently the reinterment occurred at Mount Hope Cemetery instead).
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1920s (Offsite-box 29)
  - Unprocessed files, 1880s-1920s (Offsite-box 30)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Documents related to the Centenary Methodist Episcopal Church building. Pile of insurance policies, 1900s-1910s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1920s (Offsite-box 31)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Documents concerning the incorporation of the Swedish Bethel Methodist Episcopal Church. Documents related to the New York City Society of the Methodist Episcopal Church, circa 1921. Checks, 1850s-60s.
  - Unprocessed files, 1840s-1920s (Offsite-box 32)
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1920 (Offsite-box 33)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Documents from case of 1850s in which Chauncey Smith represented Mary E. Ditchett in her lawsuit against the Spuyten Duyvil & Port Morris Railroad Company for causing the death of her husband who fell into a ditch the railroad opened and failed to secure during roadwork. Documents concerning the Prospect Avenue Methodist Episcopal Church.
  - Unprocessed files, 1860s-1920s (Offsite-box 34)
  - Unprocessed files, 1850s-1910s (Offsite-box 35)
    Holds typical mix of tri-folded bundles and loose documents on various matters. Also 6 small, original pigeonhole boxes holding documents.
  - Unprocessed files, 1840s-1920s (Offsite-box 36)